# Sk Mainul Islam

mainuliitkgp.github.io, in skmainul, mainuliitkgp

## Research Interests

I am broadly interested in Natural Language Processing and Deep Learning on Graphs. My recent research has focused on aspect based sentiment analysis, interpretability in neural NLP models, controlled text generation, concept mining and debiasing of language models.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### IIT Kharagpur

Kharagpur, India

• M.S. by Research Student, Computer Science & Engineering Supervisor: Sourangshu Bhattacharya; Research Areas: Interpretability, NLP January 2019 - Present

**∠** Email : mainulislam79@gmail.com

**♦** Mobile : +91-9635-583-571

Maulana Abul Kalam Azad University of Technology

B. Tech in Computer Science & Engineering; CGPA: 9.13

July 2014 - May 2018

#### Publications

- AR-BERT: Aspect-relation enhanced Aspect-level Sentiment Classification with Multi-modal Explanations: Sk Mainul Islam and Sourangshu Bhattacharya, TheWebConf (formerly WWW) 2022. [Link]
- Fair Data Generation using Language Models with Hard Constraints: Sk Mainul Islam, Abhinav Naqpal, Balaji Ganesan and Pranay Kumar Lohia, CtrlGen Workshop at NeurIPS 2021. [Link]

#### EXPERIENCE

#### IBM India Research Lab

Bangalore, India

GRM Intern (Remote), Mentor: Balaji Ganesan

November 2020 - Present

- o Controlled Text Generation:
  - \* Built a fair and hard constraint based language model to augment personal data entities in an unstructured text. [Demo]
  - \* Behavioural, fairness and adversarial testing verifies our proposed models' effectiveness in fair augmentation of similar entity in an adversarial setting. Our work got accepted at CtrlGen 2021 (NeurIPS-W).

## Flipkart Internet Private Limited

Bangalore, India

Summer Intern (Remote), Mentor: Lucky Dhakad

July 2021 - September 2021

- E-commerce Concept Relation Extraction:
  - \* Clustering based relation surface form extraction between two e-commerce concepts.
  - \* Adapted a BERT-based self-supervised model to extract relation surface form from internal product review data in lifestyle domain.
  - \* Mapped relation surface forms to existing relations defined in the Wikidata knowledge graph.

#### Sponsored Research and Industrial Consultancy, IIT Kharagpur

Kharagpur, India

Research Assistant

 $October\ 2018$  -  $October\ 2020$ 

- o Project: "Learning Representations from Network Data", sponsored by Intel Technology India Pvt. Ltd.
- o Principal Investigator: Prof. Niloy Ganguly, IIT Kharagpur.

## FOSSEE, IIT Bombay

Mumbai, India

Software Developer Intern

Summer 2017

o Developed a web app to port the core functionalities of Xcos (a graphic simulator) to a browser-only version that can be used without installing additional plug-ins or software on the cloud.

Kolkata, India

# Dynamic High-level E-commerce Concept Mining

Academic Collaboration Project

IIT Kharagpur, Flipkart February 2021 - Present

- Recent methods on e-commerce concept extraction fail to capture long-tail and composite concepts to properly understand the user needs.
- In this work we introduce a constrained soft clustering based concept learning model to extract composite and non-trivial concepts. (work in progress)

## Debiasing language models with smart prompt design

Stanford University April 2021 - Dec 2021

Fatima Fellowship Project, Mentors: Abubakar Abid, Firas Abuzaid

- Attribute specific bias space estimation: We estimated different attribute specific bias space by controlled swapping of attribute words and contrastive-PCA based estimation to retain user specified desirable bias.
- Post-hoc language model debiasing: We focused on post-hoc language model debiasing by subtracting attribute specific bias space from the sentence representation. This work motivated us to introduce a repository for debiasing auto-regressive language models available in Hugging Face. [Link]

## Retrieval of Derivational Nouns using Graph Based Learning

IIT Kharagpur Spring 2019

Information Retrieval Course Project

- In this project we studied the derivational morphology in English and validation of transformations by means of affixation or internal modification to retrieve derivational nouns.
- We construct a transformation graph where the nodes are source and transformed word pairs and edges are different types of transformations.
- We built a RGCN based retrieval model to infer whether any source and transformed word pair is valid or not.

### ACADEMIC SERVICES

- **Teaching Assistant**: Foundations of Algorithm Design & Machine Learning (Spring '22, '21), Computing Lab (Autumn '21), Scalable Data Mining (Autumn '20).
- Reviewer: \*SEM 2022 (invited), EMNLP 2021, NAACL 2021, EACL 2021, \*SEM 2021, EMNLP 2020.

### Computer Skills

Languages: Python, C/C++, Java, Spark/Scala, MATLAB

Toolboxes / Frameworks: Pytorch, Tensorflow, scikit-learn, Pandas, numpy, nltk

Courseworks

• Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Scalable Data Mining, Information Retrieval, Algorithm Design

### OTHER ACTIVITIES

- Active member of GEM BENCHMARK, a community driven platform aiming to improve evaluation of natural language generation.
- Mentees at ACL Year Round Mentorship program, class of 2022 ACL Mentorship.
- Participated as an official micro-blogger at ACL 2021 .
- Participated in Amazon Research Day, 2019 at Amazon India, Bangalore.